Finding Aid for the Akahori Family papers, ca. 1908-1965 LSC.2010.01
UCLA Library Special Collections
Akahori Family papers
circa 1908-1965
UCLA Library Special Collections
Akahori family
LSC.2010.01
19.5 Linear Feet (39 boxes, 1 oversize box)
Masaru Akahori was a writer, businessman, and an active member of the Japanese American community. He worked for several different Japanese language newspapers both in Japan and in the United States. He was also involved in numerous business ventures, many of which ended in failure. Following the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor, he was arrested on suspicion of being an enemy alien and incarcerated in various internment camps until March 1946. In the postwar years, he resettled his family in Los Angeles, and founded the "Town Crier," a Japanese language daily, in Little Tokyo. The collection consists of his diaries, memoirs, correspondence, business and financial records, and clippings from the many publications to which he contributed. It also includes diaries and letters written by his second wife Kiku, and various personal records relating to the Akahori family. Materials are in both English and Japanese.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Unknown
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303033606533
Biography
Masaru Akahori was born in 1884 in Tokushima Prefecture. He arrived in the United States in 1904, and worked as a reporter for a Japanese language press in Northern California for several years until returning to Japan in 1919 to work as a reporter for the "Yomiuri Shimbun" in Tokyo. He returned to America three years later, and became involved in various business ventures, many of which proved unsuccessful. These ventures included a legal office, a commercial company, and an advertising agency. Following a particularly messy financial fallout, he moved to Seattle to work for a couple of Japanese language newspapers based in the Pacific Northwest region. Immediately after the attack on Pearl Harbor, he was arrested by FBI agents as a suspect enemy alien, and thereafter moved from one internment camp to another until he was finally released in March 1946. Following the War, he and his family resettled in Los Angeles, California, and he began publishing the "Town Crier," a mimeographed Japanese language daily. Throughout his life, he went by various pen names and aliases such as: Meishu, Bennaishi, Bennosuke, Manako, and Hyoroku Oishi. He was known among his American friends as Ben. He married twice. He had two sons from his first marriage and a daughter, Tomoko Marjorie, from his second.
Kiku Akahori (née Ishizuka, 1900-1961), Masaru's second wife, was also known as Kikuko or Keybow. A native of Kanagawa Prefecture, she originally came to the United States to join her first husband, Katsu Hosaka, but divorced him in 1928 on the basis of spousal mistreatment. She looked to Masaru as a confidant and often went to him with her troubles about her first marriage. They saw and wrote to each other often and eventually married in 1935.They had one daughter between them, and remained together until her death in 1961 as a result of an illness.
Expanded Biographical Narrative
Masaru Akahori (1884-). Writer, businessman, and newspaper publisher. A native of Tokushima Prefecture, he graduated from Tokushima Chugakko [characters] [Tokushima Middle School], at which Toyohiko Kagawa, a well-known Christian social reformer and labor leader, was his senior classmate. Masaru arrived in the United States in 1904, initially resided in the San Francisco Bay Area, and later worked in Sacramento and Placerville, California, as a reporter of a Japanese language press. In 1919 he went back to Japan to work as a reporter for the" Yomiuri Shimbun" [characters] in Tokyo. He returned to America in 1922, and was involved in various business ventures in Southern California, including the Akahori Horitsu Jimusho [characters] [Akahori Legal Office] and the American Oriental Advertising Company (AOC). Many of these ventures proved unsuccessful, and his financial entanglement with business partners of the AOC resulted in his abscondence from his Terminal Island community. Subsequently, he fled to Seattle, Washington, where he became Managing Editor of the Taihoku Nippo [characters] [The Great Northern Daily News], and also served as the Pacific Northwest region correspondent of the Nichibei Shimbun [characters] [The Japanese American News] of San Francisco, one of the largest and influential Japanese language newspapers in America, until World War II broke out. Immediately after the Pearl Harbor attack, he was arrested by FBI agents as a suspected enemy alien, and was incarcerated in various internment camps, including Fort Missoula, Lordsburg, Santa Fe, and Crystal City. When he was finally released from the internment camp in March 1946, he and his family were resettled in Los Angeles. In the following month he began publishing the "Town Crier," a mimeographed Japanese language daily, in Little Tokyo. He married twice. He had two sons, Seikichi Julius and Sakuzo (both residing in Japan), from his first marriage to Mikie Miki, and a Nisei daughter, Tomoko Marjorie, from his second to Kiku Ishizuka. His pen names and aliases included: Meishu, Bennaishi, Bennosuke, Manako, and Hyroku Oishi. He was known as Ben M. Akahori among his American friends.
Scope and Content
The Akahori Family Papers are one of the largest and most significant collections of personal papers of Japanese immigrants (the Issei) included in the Japanese American Research Project (JARP) Collection housed in Library Special Collections. Particularly detailed are Masaru Akahori's diaries and memoirs, extensive files of personal correspondence, a large and comprehensive collection of documentary and printed materials regarding his wartime incarceration, hefty amounts of clippings and draft notes of his numerous publications, and fairly complete sets of business and financial records from his various attempts in venture business. The collection also contains diaries and letters written by his wife Kiku, and various correspondence and personal records relating to the Akahori family. Materials are in both English and Japanese.
Most of Akahori's prewar papers were impounded by FBI agents when he was arrested on December 7, 1942 in Seattle. Soon after he was released from the Crystal City Internment Camp in Texas in March 1946, he got in touch with the FBI and went to a designated Los Angeles warehouse, where his impounded personal papers and belongings were returned to him. He encouraged his Issei friends and acquaintances who were fellow inmates in the internment camps to do the same. However, many of them remained reluctant and afraid in the days of uncertainty, not far removed from their unpleasant experiences, to have any dealings with the FBI. This may account, in part, for the noticeable absence in the JARP Collection of comparable personal papers, records and documentary materials of other Issei.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
1. Diaries 2. Memoirs of Masaru Akahori 3. Scrapbooks and mementos compiled by Masaru Akahori 4. Personal correspondence 5. Personal records of family members 6. Writings and publishing by Masaru 7. Office records of Akahori Horitsu Jimusho 8. Stone Chemical Products Company 9. American Oriental Advertising Company (AOC) 10. Hyoroku Oishi Office 11. Columbia Commerical Company 12. Wartime internment 13. Postwar business records 14. Financial records 15. Published materials collected by Masaru Akahori
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at the Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Diaries.; Journalists -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Japanese American families -- California -- Archives.; Family papers.; Business records.; Correspondence.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles); Akahori family--Archives.; Akahori, Kikuko--Archives.; Akahori, Masaru, 1884- --Archives.; Akahori, Kikuko; Akahori, Masaru
- Diaries
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.1, 1910 (Box 1, Envelope 1)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.2, 1912 (Box 1, Envelope 2)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.3, 1920 (Box 1, Envelope 3)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.4, 1922 (Box 1, Envelope 4)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.5, 1923 (Box 1, Envelope 5)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.6, no.1, 1924 (Box 1, Envelope 6)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.6, no.2, 1924 (Box 1, Envelope 7)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.7, 1925 (Box 1, Envelope 8)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.8, 1926 (Box 2, Envelope 1)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.9, 1927 (Box 2, Envelope 2)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.10, 1928 (Box 2, Envelope 3)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.11, 1929 (Box 2, Envelope 4)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.12, 1931 (Box 2, Envelope 5)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.13, 1934 (Box 2, Envelope 6)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.14, 1938 (Box 2, Envelope 7)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.15, 1939 (Box 2, Envelope 8)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.16, no.1, 1941 (Box 2, Envelope 9)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.16, no.2, 1941 (Box 2, Envelope 10)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.17, 1949 (Box 2, Envelope 11)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.18, 1950 (Box 3, Envelope 1)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.19, 1951 (Box 3, Envelope 2)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.20, no.1, 1952 (Box 3, Envelope 3)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.20, no.2, 1952 (Box 3, Envelope 4)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.21, 1953 (Box 3, Envelope 5)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.22, 1954 (Box 3, Envelope 6)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.23, 1955 (Box 3, Envelope 7)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.24, 1956 (Box 3, Envelope 8)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.25, 1957 (Box 3, Envelope 9)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.26, no.1, 1958 (Box 4, Envelope 1)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.26, no.2, 1958 (Box 4, Envelope 2)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.26, no.3, 1958 (Box 4, Envelope 3)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.27, no.1, 1959 (Box 4, Envelope 4)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.27, no.2, 1959 (Box 4, Envelope 5)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.27, no.3, 1959 (Box 4, Envelope 6)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.28, no.1, 1960 (Box 4, Envelope 7)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.28, no.2, 1960 (Box 4, Envelope 8)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.29, no.1, 1961 (Box 4, Envelope 9)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.29, no.2, 1961 (Box 5, Envelope 1)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.30, 1962 (Box 5, Envelope 2)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.31, 1963 (Box 5, Envelope 3)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.32, 1964 (Box 5, Envelope 4)
  - Masaru Akahori, vol.33, 1965 (Box 5, Envelope 5)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.1, 1923 (Box 5, Envelope 6)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.2, no.1, 1924 (Box 5, Envelope 7)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.2, no.2, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.3, no.1, 1925 (Box 5, Envelope 9)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.3, no.2, 1925 (Box 5, Envelope 10)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.4, 1926 (Box 5, Envelope 11)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.5, 1927 (Box 5, Envelope 12)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.6, 1928 (Box 6, Envelope 1)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.7, 1929 (Box 6, Envelope 2)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.8, 1931 (Box 6, Envelope 3)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.9, 1932 (Box 6, Envelope 4)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.10, 1933 (Box 6, Envelope 5)
  - Kiku Akahori, vol.11, 1961 (Box 6, Envelope 6)
- Memoirs of Masaru Akahori
  - "Ano toki no ano koto" [characters] [It occurred at that time], 1932-1966 (Box 6, Volume 7)
  - Untitled, 1950-1966 (Box 6, Volume 8)
  - "Watakushi no odotta butai: ano toki no ano koto" [characters] [The stage on which I performed: It occurred at that time], ca.1962 (Box 6, Volume 9)
  - "Shiku hakku" [characters] [Trial and tribulation], 1932-1944 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Watakushi no odotta butai o" [characters] [The stage on which I performed], 1934-1939 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Sekkei" [characters] ['Construction'], 1957 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Scrapbooks and mementos compiled by Masaru Akahori
  - "Gikyoku: Hatto pin to Oishi Hyroku" [characters] [A play: hat pin and Oishi Hyroku], 1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Scope and Content
    The play "Hatto pin" was originally written in the late 1910's by Yoshizo Nakamura [characters], and performed in Tokyo in 1921. Two principal characters in the play were modeled after Akahori and his first wife.
  - "Taikyo sannen gakuya nikki" [characters] [Three years' stay in Tokyo], 1919 September-1922 September (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents
    A scrapbook containing memos, correspondence, and other miscellaneous papers re Akahori's three years' sojourn in Tokyo as a reporter for the "Yomiuri Shimbun."
  - "Tokyo seikatsu sannen [oyobi] Hokka nanka kiji" [characters] [Three years' stay in Tokyo and articles written for Japanese language newspapers in Northern and Southern California], 1918-1922 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    A scrapbook of correspondence, photographs and other miscellaneous papers re Masaru's stay in Tokyo from 1919 to 1922, and clippings of newspaper articles Akahori wrote for the "Hokubei hochi" [characters] and other Japanese language newspapers in California.
  - "Wagami no rekishi" [characters] [A fragment of my life story], 1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    A scrapbook containing correspondence and newspaper clippings re a beautification plan of Little Tokyo, Los Angeles, which was proposed by Akahori in 1953.
  - Large correspondence record book, 1933-1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Contains copies of Akahori's personal and business letters: - September 18, 1933-May 4, 1934, and August 22- November 24, 1941, Seattle, Washington - July 6-29, 1951, and December 23, 1953-April 21, 1959, Los Angeles, California.
  - Photographs and mementos, ca. 1932-1963 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Personal correspondence
  - From Akahori to his first wife and sons in Japan, ca. 1931-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - From Akahori to Kiku
    - Volume 1: "Haru natsu no maki" [characters] [Spring and summer], Section 1: "Kikubo no kikoku made" [characters] [Till Kiku returned to Japan], 1927 September-1928 January (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Volume 1: "Haru natsu no maki" [characters] [Spring and summer], Section 2: "Hanazukushi" [characters] [Adorned with flowers], 1928 February-March (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Volume 1: "Haru natsu no maki" [characters] [Spring and summer], Section 3: "Manofuchi" [characters] [An abyss], 1928 March 17-April 12 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Volume 1: "Haru natsu no maki" [characters] [Spring and summer], Section 4: "Nakimushi" [characters] [A cry-baby], 1928 April 23-May 15 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Volume 1: "Haru natsu no maki" [characters] [Spring and summer], Section 5: untitled, 1928 June 1-September 27 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Volume 2: "Aki no maki" [characters] [Autumn], Section 1: untitled, 1928 October 1-November 19 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Volume 2: "Aki no maki" [characters] [Autumn], Section 2: "Shuppan yori haha no futokoro made" [characters] [Sailing for Japan to be in her mother's bosom], 1928 November 10-1929 September 27 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Volume 3: "Fuyu no maki" [characters] [Winter], Section 1: "Joriku yori byoki made" [characters] [From her return to U.S. to her illness], 1929 November 14-1930 July 25 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Volume 3: "Fuyu no maki" [characters] [Winter], Section 2: Untitled, 1931 February 12-1932 November 4 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Volume 3: "Fuyu no maki" [characters] [Winter], Volume 4: "Love-nest Nikki" [characters] [Love-nest Diary], 1931-1932 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Between Akahori and Issei writers and journalists, 1929-1940 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Writers include Abiko Kyutaro, Momoi Ikken, Oka Shigeki, Okina Hisamitsu, and Sagitani Seiichi.
    - Prewar correspondence, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1928 February 27-March 19 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Condolence messages the Akahoris received upon Kiku's passing, 1961 October (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Envelopes of koden [characters] [funeral condolence money] for Kiku's passing (1 of 3), 1961 October (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Envelopes of koden [characters] [funeral condolence money] for Kiku's passing (2 of 3), 1961 October (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Envelopes of koden [characters] [funeral condolence money] for Kiku's passing (3 of 3), 1961 October (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Personal records of family members
  - Personal resumé and short biographical sketches of Akahori and his parents, ca.1943-1946 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Papers regarding Sei Fujii's deportation case, 1929 August -1931 October (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Sei Fujii, an illegal immigrant from Japan, faced deportation as a result of information obtained by the U.S. immigration authorities from Japanese informants. Akahori, together with two other Issei, were accused of being the informants and ostracized by a group of Japanese residents at a mass meeting organized by Fujii himself himself and held on December 2, 1930 in Los Angeles.
  - Akahori's insurance papers, 1927-1961 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Divorce papers, marriage certificate, and medical records belonging to Kiku (Hosaka) Akahori, Masaru's second wife., 1928-1961 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Record book on the birth of Akahori and Kiku's daughter, Tomoko Marjorie Akahori, in November 1935., 1935 November-1941 January (Box 10, Volume 9)
  - Tomoko's school work, ca.1935-1962 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Birth certificates of Seikichi Julius Akahori, first son by Akahori's first marriage, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Writings and publishing by Masaru
  - Scrapbook of clippings of newspaper articles written in Los Angeles for various Japanese language papers in California, ca. 1919-1923 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Kareshi no nikki: iminchi sanjunen shi" [characters] [His diary: Thirty years' life as an immigrant], 1939 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    A collection of essays and fiction Akahori Masaru wrote and published in magazines published by Issei in the United States. The magazines include the "Hokubei Noho" [characters] and the "Zaibei Fujin no Tomo" [characters].
  - Papers relating to the publication of "California Romance" and "This is California: Early History and Its Development into a State," books written by Akahori, ca. 1931 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Manuscripts of essays and articles written by Akahori, ca.1933-1941 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Poems written by Akahori, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Clippings of various articles written by Akahori in Japanese (1 of 2), 1933-1941 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Seihokubu Nihonjin Suisankai [Japanese Fisheries of the Northwest]
      - Correspondence regarding the Seihokubu Nihonjin Suisankai, 1934 November-1939 April (Box 16, Folder 5)
        Mostly in Japanese.
      - Notes on the discussion sessions organized by the association, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
        Includes Masaru's handwritten notes taken at and his speech drafts for these sessions.
      - U.S. Bureau of Fisheries reports on salmon fish oil, salmon, and kelp, as well as notes written by masaru onteh same subjects., 1934 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - A publication by the Canned Foods Association of Japan entitled "Fishery Industries of Japan: Salmon, Crab, Tuna, Sardine, Shellfish and Fishmeal", 1935 (Box 16, Folder 8)
        In English.
      - Research reports on the shark industry with Masaru's notes, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        In English and Japanese.
      - Research articles written by Japanese authors on the fishing industry, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 2)
        Includes "What the Drill Is and Does" and a report on bonita by H. Shiihara as well as "Canned Tuna Fish 'Honeycomb'" by Shitoku Yera. In English and Japanese.
      - "Smelt and Herring Regulations" and "Game Farm Regulations" of the State of Washington, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Study notes and short reports written by Masaru on various fisheries topics, ca.1934-1938 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Manuscripts of Masaru's articles on the fishing industry in Japan and the U.S., ca.1933-1938 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Leaflets of articles written by Masaru published by the Suisankai, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Financial papers of the Suisankai, ca.1934-1938 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Clippings of various articles written by Akahori in Japanese (2 of 2), 1933-1941 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - A collection of Japanese leaflets printed in San Francisco and Los Angeles, ca.1914-1941 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "Taihoku Nippo" [characters] [Great Northern News]
    - Correspondence relating to the "Taihoku Nippo", 1935 July-1941 September (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Papers regarding the paroles of Eika Chiba and Unokichi Tanaka, 1934 November-1941 July (Box 12, Folder 4)
      Eika Chiba was an inmate of the state penitentiary at Walla Walla, Washington, charged with a felony and given a life sentence. Unokichi Tanaka as an inmate at the Folsom Prison in California charged with murder and given a life sentence. Akahori, as managing editor of the "Taihoku Nippo," petitioned for their parole hearings. Correspondence included is mostly between Akahori and Chiba.
    - Manuscript by Shoryu Matsui entitled "Sugishi nichiro kowasho no kangai" [characters] [Reminiscence of the past: the Portsmouth Peace Conference of 1906] for publication in the "Taihoku Nippo", ca.1941 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Fictions and short essays written by Akahori published in the "Taihoku Nippo", 1935-1941 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori on various topics (1 of 2), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      Topics include: alien land laws in the state of Washington; the visit of Prince Chichibu (the Emperor's brother); a murder committed by a Japanese in Auburn, California; and the visit of a training ship from Japan.
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori on various topics (2 of 2), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - A scrapbook of "Taihoku Nippo" articles, 1933-41, 1933-1941 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - "Natsu no kashu o kataru" [characters] [California in the summer], a collection of articles from the "Taihoku Nippo" (1 of 2), 1939 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - "Natsu no kashu o kataru" [characters] [California in the summer], a collection of articles from the "Taihoku Nippo" (2 of 2), 1939 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Clippings on various topics relating to the fishing industry, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Many are from the "Taihoku Nippo."
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori (1 of 6), undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Mostly editorials.
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori (2 of 6), undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori (3 of 6), undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori (4 of 6), undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori (5 of 6), undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori (6 of 6), undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori, ca.1933-1941 (1 of 2) (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Many of them a part of the "Nippon rekishi monogatari" [characters] [Japanese history stories] series.
    - Clippings of "Taihoku Nippo" articles written by Akahori, ca.1933-1941 (2 of 2) (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Financial papers of the "Taihoku Nippo", 1938-1939 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - "Nichibei Shimbun" [characters] [Japanese American News]
    - Correspondence exchanged between Hyoroku Oishi (Masaru) and Shichinosuke Asano, editor of the "Nichibei", 1937 Februrary-1938 June (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Masaru's memos as well as correspondence exchanged between Akahori and the editorial and managerial staff of the "Nichibei", 1937 April-1938 September (Box 15, Folder 3)
      Correspondence regards the question of establishing the company's Pacific Northwest Branch in Seattle.
    - Memos and manuscripts of articles written by Akahori for the "Nichibei", 1937-1939 (Box 15, Folder 4)